<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians strength. By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21833</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852020</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17320</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1394:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians strength. By William Sclater. Batchelar of Diuinity and minister of the word of God at Pitmister in Somerset</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1575-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17320:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS STRENGTH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> WILLIAM SCLATER.</p>
            <p>BATCHELAR OF DIVINITY <hi>and Miniſter of the word of God at</hi> PIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISTER <hi>in Somerſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of the University of Oxford</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1612:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17320:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17320:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>WILLIAM HILL</hi> ESQVIRE, at PITMISTER in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> grace and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, a weaker creature then man in <hi>Adam,</hi> the world affords not: a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then a Chriſtian, a man in Chriſt the earth beares not. The ſtrong men of <hi>David</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. Sam. 23.8.</note> are in ſcriptures renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: yet what were their conqueſts, but over Gyants or fell beaſts? Wee fight not againſt fleſh and bloud: wee encounter and conquer, yea<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8 37.</note> overconquer the<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 4 4.</note> God of this world. Principalities and powers, our head-ſtrong ſelues, we rule, yea overrule, thorough Chriſt that raigneth in vs. The mighteſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g naturaliſts, if abaſures haue not deiected, yet honors haue puffed vp: if penury hath not diſtracted, yet plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath bewitched. But<note n="d" place="margin">Phil 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>we know how to abound, and how to bee abaſed: how to be full, and how to ſuffer neede.</hi> We can doe all things in Chriſt that ſtrengthneth vs. It is ſaid of ſome of <hi>Davids</hi> worthies,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Sam. 23.19</note> they reached not to the firſt three. Nor we (we muſt confeſſe) to the Apoſtles meaſure: but yet we haue all received of <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſpirit of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> every one his meaſure, according to the meaſure of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb facs="tcp:17320:3"/>of Chriſt. It ſhall behooue vs to know our ſtrength ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actuall or poſſible to all dueties neceſſary to ſalvation, that the idle pretenſe of abſolute infirmity make vs not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely preſumptuous. And it nearely concernes vs, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the fountaine thereof, <hi>the mighty God in our weakenes perfitting his power:</hi> leaſt ſelfeconceit make vs over confident in adventures; or vnthankfulnes, careleſſe to referre our abilities to his glory. That comfort alſo would bee meditated, that the ſupply of ſtrength is certaine when it is humbly ſought, where &amp; how it ought: that no ſluggiſh feare of the Adverſary diſmay vs in the encounter. To this ſumme amounts this whole ſermon.<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.10, 11.</note> Now the God of all grace that hath called you to this eternall glory by Chriſt Ieſus make you perfect, confirme, ſtrengthen, and ſtabliſh you. To him be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and dominion for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips in the trueſt loue, <hi>WILLIAM SCLATER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17320:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. 4.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I can doe all things through Chriſt which ſtrengthneth mee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the ſpeech of the Apoſtle not vainly boaſting of his ſtrength na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, but thankefully acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the power of Gods grace in him.</p>
            <p>And howſoever our ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle reach not to this Apoſtolicall quantum, yet is it in ſome meaſure verified of all Gods children; <hi>They can doe all things through Chriſt which ſtrengthneth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words, for order and more diſtinct handling, obſerue foure things, 1. The bleſſing acknowledged; power and abilitie I can doe. 2. The extent of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the obiect; <hi>All things.</hi> 3. The fountaine of the bleſſing; <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 4. The continuall ſupply of the bleſſing, in the deſcription of Chriſt by his effect; <hi>through Chriſt which ſtrengthneth.</hi> Of the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I haue ſtrength to doe all things. Man in his naturals is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a creature made of frailties. View him in his anatomy, yee ſhal ſee nothing of moralities but meere privations.<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>He knowes not nor can know the things of the ſpirit of God.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>He thinks nor can thinke as of himſelfe a good thought.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſubmits not, nor can ſubmit to the law of God.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>He wils not nor can will things pleaſing vnto God. He grieues not nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grieue for the offence of God. He feares not nor can feare the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God. Hee doth not nor can doe things acceptable vnto God.</hi> And yet of man reformed it is true; <hi>Hee can doe all things through Chriſt which ſtrengthneth.</hi> By nature, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17320:4"/>by grace, omnipotent, ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Ser. in Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tic. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> 
               <hi>without Chriſt nothing;</hi> in Chriſt he can all things. <hi>I can doe all things.</hi> So mightie is God in mans weakneſſe, able to enable the weakeſt creature, to the ſtrongeſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances.</p>
            <p>Let me apply it thus. There are amongſt vs at this day many ſtrange and vnheard of opinions touching obſeſſion &amp; poſſeſſion of mens bodies by Divels; ſome holding, as they thinke, not without probabilitie, that there is now no poſſeſſion or obſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordinary. Neither my Text nor purpoſe leades to diſcuſſe that controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. But however that be, this once I am ſure of; There are many helliſh ſpirits whether poſſeſſing or infeſting the ſoules of men. Wee read of<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 13.11.</note> 
               <hi>a ſpirit of infirmitie</hi> a woman was poſſeſſed withall; the weaker veſſell, with a ſpirit of weakneſſe. And this ſpirit is rife almoſt in all men profeſſing Communion with Chriſt by his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>There are ſome, ſaith <hi>Iſay,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſai 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>mighty to drinke wine, &amp; ſtrong to poure in ſtrong drinke.</hi> Reproue; Theſe men ſo ſtrong in lewdneſſe, pretend for themſelues infirmitie in grace; Beare with me; it is mine infirmitie. There are tongues, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iames,</hi> ſet on fire of hell. I haue heard, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> the blaſphemy of the multitude. And who hath eares to heare, but hee heares fearefull oathes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e out, as the flowers of ſpeech, and the gracing <hi>praeludia</hi> of common conference? Reproue; What heare we, but infirmitie pretended? It is true, you ſay, ſwearing is nought; but beare with me, it is my infirmitie. Beloved in Chriſt Ieſus; ſuch ſpirits of infirmitie, are helliſh ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; <hi>Gods ſpirit it is a ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">2. Tim. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>of power.</hi> And where he dwels, either in <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> they can doe all things. I freely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17320:4"/>acknowledge, there are infirmities in the ſtrongeſt of Gods children; yea, if I ſaid, all actuall ſinnes of Gods children are in them infirmities, I ſhould not much erre: but yet there goe many ſinnes masked vnder colour of infirmities, which neerely lookt on, deſcrie themſelues to be preſumptious. Suffer mee therefore a little to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry vnto you, what are theſe infirmities that may ſtand with grace; what weakneſſes thoſe are, that are ſeene in theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe ſtrong ones of the Lord. Beſides theſe inevitable luſtings of the fleſh againſt the ſpirit, which no ſtrength of grace in any, was ever able to ſuppreſſe: another ſort of them there is, incident to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; groſſe and notorious ſinnes in themſelues, though in Gods children ſinnes of weakneſſe. You may thus diſcover them; Infirmities (I ſpeake now of groſſe, and notorious ſinnes, that may deſerue this favorable title of infirmities) infirmities truly ſo called, are vſually ſins of incogitancie, beſides the purpoſe of a regenerate Chriſtian: &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal. 6.1.</hi> Tentatio fallie &amp; praeoccupat neſcientes. Aug. de peccat. merit &amp; Remiſſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If any be prevented,</hi> taken ere he is aware, in a ſlip of infirmitie, ſaith <hi>Paule,</hi> deſcribing infirmities of Gods children: they are therefore vſually ſinnes beſides the purpoſe gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all or particular. Such thoſe of <hi>David,</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter;</hi> infirmities no doubt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though enormities in themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Davids</hi> adultery<note n="l" place="margin">2. Sam. 11.2.</note> not thought of, before ſuggeſted. <hi>Peters</hi> deniall<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 26.35.</note> purpoſed againſt; <hi>Though I ſhould die with thee I would not deny thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when men ſhall plot iniquitie, and<note n="n" place="margin">Mic. 2.1.</note> faſhion it on their beds; when, as<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 27.41.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau,</hi> they hunt after opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and purpoſely ſtudy how to compaſſe their noto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious ſins: theſe ſhould not I dare cal ſins of infirmity.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17320:5"/>
            <p>In ſinnes of infirmitie,<note place="margin">Premit &amp; vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get infirmos, Aug. qua ſupra.</note> as the temptation is ſuddaine, ſo the conſent not without ſome reluctation wreſted from them, and ever there is more or leſſe reſiſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſent.<note n="p" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3, 9.</note> Hee that is borne of God ſinneth not, nor can ſinne. <hi>i.</hi> ſay ſome, not make a trade of ſinning; ſay others, not ſin to death; this I may adde, not with fulneſſe of conſent, not without ſome reluctation. And theſe ſinnes thus ſtriven againſt, are indeed infirmities in Gods children, how ever enormious in themſelus. By the law of God,<note n="q" place="margin">Deut 22.26, 27.</note> a Virgin found in the field, ſuddainely and violently aſſaulted, if according to ſtrength ſhee make reſiſtance, crying out, and none neere to help her, in ſuch caſe is reputed guiltleſſe of the crime of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And if we by violent aſſaults be withdrawne, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving to the vtmoſt of power receaved, to withſtand, &amp; yet fal; of ſuch fals we may ſay as <hi>David,</hi> they are our infirmities. But if we ſhall wait for occaſions, and bid welcome to opportunities; as the ſtrumpet in <hi>Salomon,</hi> to her adulterous copeſmate,<note n="r" place="margin">Prov 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>I came forth to meete theo; I haue ſought thy face, and reioyce that I haue found thee:</hi> ſuch ſinnes dare any call infirmities?</p>
            <p>Sinnes of weakneſſe, (I ſpeake ſtill of notorious and groſſe ſinnes) haue commonly for their ground, ſome ſtrong paſſion in nature; ſomething that is with nature very prevalent; as feare of death in <hi>Peter,</hi> of ſhame in <hi>David.</hi> That ſame which the Philoſopher cals moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible of all evils, prevailed with<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and overcame him;<note n="t" place="margin">Iob. 2.4.</note> skin for skin and all that a man hath, will hee giue for his life. and that ſhame, which ingenuous natures feare more then death, no marvaile, ſo prevalent with <hi>David.</hi> But what ſhall we ſay of ſinnes abhorred of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17320:5"/>that ſame vnmeaſurable and Dutchmanlike drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king? Of this ſhall we ſay it is an infirmitie?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Sinnes of infirmitie, as in their temptation they are ſuddaine and reſiſted: ſo in their looſe, they giue farewell in bitterneſſe; they ende in mourning.<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 26.27.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> bitter banning coſt him bitter weeping: and <hi>Davids</hi> ſweet ſin was<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> ſowerly ſauced.<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Eth.</hi> 2.1</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>But when men<note n="y" place="margin">Philip. 3 19.</note> ſhall glory in their ſhame; &amp; as the buyer in <hi>Salomon, It is naught, It is naught;</hi> but when hee is gone he boaſteth: this I ſhould never call a ſinne of infirmitie.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Sinnes of infirmitie, are never ſinnes of cuſtome,<note place="margin">Noeſuit aliquae do ebrius, qud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis abſit vt fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ebrioſus. Aug. de peccat. merit &amp; remiſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> yea ſeldome or never iterated (I ſpeake ſtill of groſſe ſinnes, notoriouſly knowne to be enormious:) but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification is ever there planted, where the breach hath once beene made. Of <hi>Iudah</hi> his inceſt we read, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 38.26.</note> that he never came more neere <hi>Thamar.</hi> Now whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſhall<note n="a" place="margin">Iſai. 5.11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> follow drunkenneſſe;<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 23. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke it yet ſtill:</hi> howe ſhall we call theſe infirmities?</p>
            <p>And as, for ſinnes, they haue ſtrength to avoid them; ſo for duties, they haue power to practiſe. The queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that Chriſt propounded to the ſonnes of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> if it be moved to any of Gods children, will receaue the ſame anſwere with the ſame or more truth.<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 20.22.</note> 
               <hi>Can you drinke of the cup that I ſhall drinke of? and bee baptiſed with the baptiſme that I ſhall be baptiſed with?</hi> They anſwer, we can. <hi>Canſt thou moderate thy affections? refraine thy lips? ſubdue thy thoughes to the obedience of Chriſt?</hi> Surely theſe (and what not?) can a child of God do in ſome meaſure. So that it is but hypocriſie, that pretends abſolute diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17320:6"/>And of the bleſſing acknowledged thus farre.</p>
            <p>See we now the extent of the bleſſing in the obiect. <hi>All things.</hi> Strangely is <hi>Paules</hi> voice changed. In one place he thus complaines,<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>To will is preſent with me, but I finde no power to performe: yet here he triumphs; I can doe all things.</hi> We may thus reconcile them. 1. It may bee, that is a negatiue by compariſon, as ſuch are obvious every where in Scripture. And the meaning may bee, not that hee had no power, but none anſwerable to his will: as elſe where;<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 9.41.</note> 
               <hi>If yee were blind yee ſhould haue no ſin .i.</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> none in compariſon, not ſimply none. And ſurely as in men aliens from the life of God, there is an endleſſe deſire to ſinne, (which makes their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment endleſſe,) though their power in execution be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained: So in Gods children, though wee ſee ſome performances, more endeavours; yet endleſſe deſires, &amp; never ſatisfied with their meaſure of obedience: they will, but finde no power anſwerable to their deſire. Or 2 thus: To will is preſent, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to goe through with the worke,<note place="margin">Non ait facere, ſed perficere bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, dug. Cont. Iulian pelag. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> they find not. God having reſerved per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection of power, to the world to come. <hi>All things. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> falling on this Scripture, infer preſently a poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by grace, to keepe the law to iuſtification: for what ſhould he want to righteouſneſſe, that can all things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined in the law of God? Not to trouble you with that controverſy at large, take only what may ſerue for loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their hold on this Scripture.</p>
            <p>Some here acknowledge <hi>vniverſale accommodum;</hi> the vniverſall particle, reſtrained to the particulars men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. <hi>All things .i.</hi> all theſe things. And it is true, there are in Scriptures plentifull examples of ſuch reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17320:6"/>But yet I ſee no great neceſſitie or warrant, in this place, to run to ſuch limitation. This once I am ſure of: the things here ſpecified, are of as difficult performance as any, J knowe, in the whole circle of Chriſtian duties. Aequabilitie in all ſtates; what hath Chriſtianity harder? Not to ſurfet of proſperitie; what temperance? Not to be deiected with abaſures; of how great fortitude? And he that can theſe: may, without reſtraint, profeſſe his power in all the reſt.</p>
            <p>Some therefore in this queſtion thus diſtinguiſh performance of the law. It is of two ſorts. One after legall rigour: another after Evangelicall mitigation. That is<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.3.</note> impoſſible: for when<note n="g" place="margin">Gal 3.10.</note> one duty may not bee wanting, and<note n="h" place="margin">Iac. 3.2.</note> in many things we ſinne all, who can by the law expect iuſtification? After Evangelicall mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it's poſſible to doe all things; yet not ſo as to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified thereby.</p>
            <p n="1">As 1. it is poſſible to loue the law &amp; the duties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained.<note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 119.37.</note> 
               <hi>Lord ſaith David, how doe I loue thy law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Poſſible to purpoſe obedience.<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 119.106.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſworne, and am ſtedfaſtly purpoſed, to keepe thy righteous iudgements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Poſſible to deſire obedience:<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>To will is preſent with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Poſſible to endeavour obedience:<note n="m" place="margin">Act 24 16. Phil. 3, 13.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>I ſtriue and wreſtle with my Corruptions that I may keepe a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 Poſſible in a meaſure to performe obedience: for we haue<note n="n" place="margin">2. Tim. 1.7.</note> a ſpirit of power.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Poſſible to<note n="o" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.11.</note> grieue for defects. And this is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble performance at the barre of mercy: though ſuch as cannot but dread the cenſure of exact Iuſtice, to which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17320:7"/>they are all liable, that ſeek iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the law.<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. merit. &amp; remiſſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad Calcem.</note> 
               <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum eſt vt fiat, conandum eſt vt fiat, ſupplicandum eſt vt fiat: non tamen quaſi factum fuerit confidendum eſt.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thus; Acceptably we may; perfectly we cannot. And it is true there may bee acceptation where is not perfection;<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ready minde is accepted: and that of the Lord by the Prophet;<note n="r" place="margin">Mal 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>I will ſpare, as a father doth his ſonne that ſerveth him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which if I may adde one thing for explanation, I thinke the anſwere wilbe beyond exception. Conſider we therefore in every chriſtian duty, two things; 1. <hi>Rem,</hi> 2. <hi>Modum:</hi> the ſubſtance of the duty, the manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The things are al poſſible in a meaſure: and yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible in that perfect, and full meaſure that the law requires. For<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 20.9.</note> whoſe hart is clean? Or who dares<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 143.2.</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his beſt works to be iudged without mercy? &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſcribes not feelingly to that <hi>vae</hi> of a father? <hi>Vae etiam laudabili vitae hominum, ſi remotâ miſericordiâ diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutias cam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet for the duties, ſome meaſure there is of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and hearty performance. <hi>Bernard</hi> blaſphemed not when he ſaide, Chriſt makes beleevers omnipotent.<note n="u" place="margin">Ser. in Cant. <hi>85.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is nothing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wherein the omnipotency of the word more ſhines, then in this; that he makes after a ſort omnipotent, all that truſt in him.</hi> All things are poſſible to a beleever. <hi>An non omnipotens cui omnia poſſibilia?</hi> Surely ſo is every beleeving new borne chriſtian, in his kinde, omnipotent: not as God, with a tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcendent pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er beſeeming the deity; but with all ſufficiency neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to chriſtianity. <hi>They can do all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now brethren, if I had leaue, a little largely to apply
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17320:7"/>this vniverſality; me thinks it would not be hard by it to diſcover the hypocriſie of many, pretending vnion and communion with Chriſt.<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 12.6.</note> Shibboleth never deſcryed ſo many Ephraimites, as this woulde hypocrites in the Church of God.<note n="x" place="margin">Gell. Attic. noct. lib. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Phauorinus</hi> in <hi>Gellius,</hi> ſeeing a nice mother willing to ſhare her motherly offices betwixt her ſelfe and her nurſe, thus angerly cries out; <hi>Quod nam inquit, eſt hoc contra naturam imperfectum &amp; dimidiatum matrum genus?</hi> What a halfe kinde of mothers againſt nature is this; that brings forth, and forthwith caſts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her the birth of her owne wombe? Such a <hi>dimidiatum Chriſtianorum genus,</hi> a halfe kinde of Chriſtians, ye ſhal every where ſee; cut of ſhorter in their practiſe, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were the garmentes of <hi>Davids</hi> ſervantes by <hi>Hanun.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Act. 26.28.</note> 
               <hi>Agrippa,</hi> as now the rate of chriſtians goes, nere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a prime place in the Church of God; and<note n="z" place="margin">Mar. 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>Herods</hi> many things might iuſtly require a preachers conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence at his inceſt with <hi>Herodias.</hi> But yet by <hi>Paules</hi> rule, neither better then hypocrits.<note n="a" place="margin">2. Reg 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>Naaman</hi> in one thing would be borne withall. And howſoever the Prophet ſpeake peace vnto him, vpon <hi>hypotheſis</hi> of his contrarie purpoſe: yet <hi>S. Iames</hi> is reſolute; that the<note n="b" place="margin">Iac. 2.10.</note> willing bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with our ſelues in one thing, argues a meere nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſincere obedience. And what availes it, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whether covetouſnes or prodigality, prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or hypocriſie raigne in vs? whether on the right hand; or on the left; by overgoig, or vndergoing; we be deprived of ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? There are many by-pathes miſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a chriſtian: but they meere all in one terme; the<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 16.25.</note> 
               <hi>iſſues of them all are the iſſues of death.</hi> What profits it to fly preciſenes, and incurre profanenes? As if a man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17320:8"/>fled from a Lyon and a Beare met him, as the Prophet ſpeakes in another caſe.</p>
            <p>Yea this let me more ſay, could we go as farre in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere practiſe, as the young man in the goſpell went in prowde profeſſion;<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 19.20.</note> 
               <hi>All theſe things haue I done, from my youth vp;</hi> and yet one thing wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting: thoſe other things ſhould no whit availe vs. Grace breeds no monſters: as it is not redundant in ſuperfluities, ſo neither defectiue <hi>in neceſsarijs.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.7.</note> You are behinde in no gift; it is the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſcription of every truely renued chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Wee haue many amongſt vs in pretence new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and yet well weighed, but monſters of new men. The good heart goes farre, when the whole outwarde man is vnreformed. I know it is true of the heart even in this ſecond generation, it is <hi>primum vivens:</hi> but yet I could never finde a cleere fountaine, but the ſtreames were alſo in ſome meaſure purged.<note n="f" place="margin">Iac. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Can a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine?</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Iames;</hi> and can<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 12.35.</note> a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the good treaſure of his good hart, but bring forth good things? The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Bethel</hi> were naught &amp; vnholeſome; &amp; the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by them made barren. What marvel? whilſt the ſprings were filthy.<note n="h" place="margin">2. Reg. 2.21.</note> But when <hi>Eliſha</hi> had caſt his ſalt into the ſprings; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I haue healed the waters, Death ſhall no more come therof, nor barrennes to the ground.</hi> The heart vnſanctified, is no better then a ſinke of vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, alwaies foaming out ſhame and filthines. But when once the Lord hath ſeaſoned the heart with grace, the ſtreames that thence flow, are health and holines.<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heart is ſprinkled from an evill conſcience, the body is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo waſhed with pure water.</hi> And how many? alas, how ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, bare tonguy Chriſtians? Linguiſts only, in religion?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17320:8"/>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iac. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Be warmed, be filled,</hi> is all their charity; a little of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Canaan,</hi> all their ſanctity. He is a monſter in nature, that is bigger tongued then handed. And they are monſters in grace, whoſe tongues ſwel with prowd boaſtings of holineſſe; and their right hands are right hands of iniquity. Beloved, heare <hi>Peters</hi> exhortation:<note n="l" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ioine to faith vertue, to vertue knowledge, to knowledge te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance; &amp;c: Virtutes chriſtianae</hi> are <hi>Copulativae;</hi> and ſo lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in amity each to other; that as <hi>Nami</hi> ſpeaks to <hi>Ruth;</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth 1.16.</hi> Qui vnam vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem habet, Aug. ep. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> where thou goeſt, I go; <hi>where thou dwelleſt, I dwell; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death can ſever.</hi> So where one dwels, al dwell; where one is wanting, no one is obtained. Paſſe we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third member; the fountaine of the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifica that <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeakes of himſelfe; and ſuch ſpeeches as theſe of himſelfe, made <hi>Porphyrie</hi> charge him with the crime of boaſting. But yet this ſhall ever be noted as the nature of thankfulneſſe; It is willing to draw out received benefits to the vtmoſt extent; but ſtill with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the praiſe of the beſtower. <hi>I can do all things,</hi> but the fountaine of this power is Chriſt. So els where;<note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.10</note> 
               <hi>I haue laboured more then all: yet not I, but grace which is with me.</hi> And what if we ſay with <hi>Bernard,</hi> we are not only<note n="o" place="margin">Bern. de grat. &amp; lib. arbit.</note> 
               <hi>operis miniſtri per effectum,</hi> but <hi>operantis quodam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſocij per conſenſum.</hi> If this be withal acknowledged, that God Communicates the worke vnto vs, and that will and worke proceed from him.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Aug. de haereſ. cap. <hi>88.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pelagius</hi> in <hi>Auſtins</hi> old age, ſet this hereſy on foot; that man in nature, as now borne of <hi>Adam,</hi> hath power of himſelfe, to keepe all the Commandements. From him it ſhould ſeeme the Greekes tooke their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17320:9"/>and that naturall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſelfe abilitie and ſufficiency, which they dreamed to be in nature, even to things ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall, as beliefe and repentance. My purpoſe is not to run out into the large diſcuſſing of that contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie; this only, it will not be amiſſe to ſhew, how farre natures ſtrength reacheth in moralities, and to what it extends not. This then I thinke may be granted to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> without any preiudice of truth. That naturall me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſome kind of command over the locomotiue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie; and may doe the externall workes of piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and iuſtice to men, without any more then the generall influence of providence, or the common worke of Gods ſpirit, which is vouchſafed to hypocrits in the Church, yea to ſome heathen out of it. The<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles by nature .i.</hi> by inſtinct, direction, power of nature, <hi>doe the things of the law.</hi> I ſay not all things; I ſay not any thing in the right manner. Yet <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpake much, if performance were anſwerable: <hi>Si ſcirem Deos ignoſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, homines ignoraturos: tamen propter peccati turpitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem peccare dedignarer:</hi> Were J ſure of pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fom God, and concealement from men; yet for the turpitude ſin hath in it, I would ſcorne to commit it. <hi>Magna ſunt haec in homine Philoſopho:</hi> and a ſaying as neere as any to chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſinceritie.</p>
            <p>But yet if this be true, that <hi>principium &amp; finis deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant actionem,</hi> the motiue and ende denominate the action: nature will never reach; I ſay not; to do al things, but not to doe any thing morally good, or acceptable to God. The principles of moral actions, that they may be acceptable according to the law, are two; Loue, and Dutie. Loue inclining the affections; Duty preſſing the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17320:9"/>conſcience. And how of loue to God we ſhould do du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that haue not had Gods loue ſhed abroad in our hearts, I know not: ſeeing <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note n="r" place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.19.</note> wee loue him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loved vs firſt. And who ever could finde a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man ſo rectifyed; as that he performed his religious or civil offices, for conſcience of God?</p>
            <p>The end is<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> Gods glory. And if ever heathen or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified men come thus farre, to ſuch intention, <hi>Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> ſhall ſoone be acknowledged a teacher of truth. <hi>Dulce &amp; decorum, honeſtum</hi> and <hi>honorificum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virtutes iſtae ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li fine turpes &amp; defermes. Aug. cont. Iulian. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi> Non oſſiciis ſed ſinibus a vitiis diſcernendae virtutes. Idem ibidem.</note> vaine glory and eternitie of fame; theſe were motiues heatheniſh. But for Gods glory, who ſo findes in nature a deſire to advance it; findes more then the Lord himſelfe coulde finde in his moſt ſtrict ſurview of man in his naturals:<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 14 2 3.</note> 
               <hi>There is none that vnderſtandeth, none that ſeeketh after God.</hi> And what lacke Papiſts of <hi>Pelagianiſme;</hi> that allow to nature a power diſpoſitiue, and ability to prepare it ſelfe to regeneration? The Apoſtle, that<note n="u" place="margin">Philip. 3.6.</note> in nature went as farre as any; yet acknowledgeth all his power to proceed from Chriſt. And our Saviour himſelfe,<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> Without me yee can doe nothing; no, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,<note n="x" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>not thinke a good thought.</hi> And howſoever it bee true, Gods children haue power to practiſe: yet is the fountaine of all power Chriſt Ieſus. On him firſt reſted<note n="y" place="margin">Iſai. 11.2.</note> the ſpirit of ſtrength, and<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 1 16.</note> of his fulneſſe wee all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue grace for grace; grace be it what it will bee;<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 4.7.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of the donation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now brethren beloved &amp; longed for, what remains for vs: but<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 116.12, 13</note> 
               <hi>to take the cup of Salvation, and giue thankes vnto the Lord?</hi> It is all the recompence the Lord expects from vs, for all the bleſſings he hath beſtowed on vs. It
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17320:10"/>may be, we can ſay, ſome of vs, that the bloody fluxe of naturall corruption is ſtopped in vs; we ſhall be vnthak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if we acknowledge not<note n="c" place="margin">Mark. 5.30.</note> the vertue to haue come from Chriſt. It may be, wee can ſay our lips are purged; that we can now ſpeake to the praiſe of the Lord: but <hi>Iſai</hi> would acknowledge<note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 6 6.</note> that the coale came from this Altar. It may be that we haue receaved<note n="e" place="margin">Iſai. 50 4.</note> a tongue of the learned but can we forget that the Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it? It may be a ſpirit and power in prayer: but ſhall we not remember, that it is the<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> ſpirit that helpes our infirmities? Yea go over all the good things thou inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſt, thou ſhalt be forced to acknowledge Chriſt for the fountaine. And why may I not againe inferre; that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our rivers flowe all from this ſea, they ſhould<note n="g" place="margin">Ec. 1.7.</note> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther return, as tributaries, whence they firſt proceeded? my meaning is, the guifts we haue receaved fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, we ſhould vſe all<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 11. vlt</note> to the honour of him from whome we haue receaved them. It is good in Chriſtianity, in ſome ſenſe, to circulate: and if in the vſe of our guifts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved, we could make our whole life a circle, to cloſe in the point whence it began, the motion were heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This doe then. Marſhall vp your graces that you haue receaved: ſet them as the Cherubims on the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſeat,<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 25.20.</note> each facing another, all with their faces turned to Chriſt. <hi>Zeale and knowledge, faith and charity,</hi> let each looke to other: <hi>knowledge,</hi> to direct <hi>zeale; zeale,</hi> to vſe knowledge to the glory of him, that hath enlightned our eies to ſee, and enflamed our hearts to loue him in truth.</p>
            <p>The laſt member remaines: the ſupply of the bleſſing in the deſcription of Chriſt by his effect; <hi>Chriſt which ſtrengthneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17320:10"/>
            <p>Chriſt ſtrengthneth two waies: 1. by infuſing habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtrength; I meane, by giving the habits of graces whereby we are fitted to do all things required of vs to ſalvation, as <hi>faith, patience, charity &amp;c.</hi> 2, by giving vſe of theſe gifts, when occaſion requireth. Both are here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; but this latter rather to be inſiſted on. Whence obſerue two things: 1. the neceſſity; 2. the certainety of Chriſts aſſiſtence in practiſe of chriſtian duties.</p>
            <p>Neceſſity, even after grace received. So that when a man is indued with habituall faculties: yet is not he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled for any actuall performance without ſpeciall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence of Chriſt by his ſpirit. <hi>See Ioh. 15.5. Phi. 2.13.</hi> the places are known. No one act of faith, patience, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. but hath neede of Chriſts ſpeciall aſſiſtence for right performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>Titus</hi> had received the habit of loue: yet<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.16.</note> thanks be to God (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that hath put into the heart of Titus this care for you. Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks excellently to this purpoſe:<note n="l" place="margin">De grat. &amp; lib Arbit. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſine illo vel operante vt veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, vel cooperante cum volumus, ad bona pietatis opera ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil valemus.</hi> The altar of the ſanctuary, at the baſe, had Lyons of braſſe for ſupporters; It may be, as types of Chriſt, the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſupporting vs in every particular action of worſhip acceptable to God. The church is deſcribed comming out of the wildernes of this world,<note n="m" place="margin">Cant. 8.5.</note> leaning on her beloved. <hi>Bernard</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies elegant; not alwaies apt: in this gloſſe, me thinks, aptnes and elegancie haue met togither; <hi>Fruſtra nititur ſi non innitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is vaine to attempt one ſtep without this ſtaffe to leane on.<note place="margin">Petrus ex egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio praeſumpto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re creber nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor effectus. Aug ep. <hi>120.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> lamentable experience is evidence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; preſuming but a litle of himſelfe, we know how
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17320:11"/>fowly he fell. There is an hereſie about providence, that God indeed giues to every creature the firſt power and ability of moving; but after that once given, affords no more but generall influence, for vſing the faculties received. The Lord confutes it in <hi>Ieroboam;</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1. Reg. 13.4.</note> ſtretching out his hand to ſmite the Prophet, but not able to pull it in. Not much vnlike is that hereſie about the grace of God: that God indeed preve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts with grace, but needs not ſupply vs with grace ſubſequent for actuall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances. Would God our own dayly wofull experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were not too plentifull confutation of this errour. Alas how often finde we it true, That we would doe good, <hi>but</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>evill is ſo preſent with vs, that we are not able to performe it?</hi> How many holy purpoſes faile of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through Gods iuſt withholding his aſſiſting grace for our pride and vnthankfulnes?</p>
            <p>Whiles <hi>Moſes</hi> was praying in the mount, at <hi>Ioſuah</hi> his great battell with the Amalekites, his<note n="p" place="margin">Ex, 17.12.</note> hands grew feeble, and <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> were faine to ſupport them. Beloved, not <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur,</hi> but Chriſt himſelfe muſt ſupport vs, if in any action we deſire performance. This do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thou read, or heare, or pray, or practiſe, <hi>à Chriſto principium:</hi> pray Chriſt to ſtrengthen, and giue ability for performance. That which remaines, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract into this ſhort compendium: We haue heard the neceſſity; ſee we now the certainty of Chriſts aſſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in every neceſſary duty of chriſtianity, our indeavours being adioined. Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth; ſo certain is aſſiſtence where a chriſtian indeavours.</p>
            <p>And let it be our incouragement in all neceſſary du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, how difficult ſo ever they ſeem to vs. It is the fault
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17320:11"/>of many to forbeare indeavours, thorough deſpaire of performance. And, as the ſluggard in <hi>Salomon,</hi> we are ever in chriſtianity fancying difficulties, a great deale more then the duties containe. <hi>A Lyon is in the way, &amp;c.</hi> It is a ſweet <hi>epithet</hi> here given to Chriſt: he is ſtrong in himſelfe, and giues ſtrength to vs;<note n="q" place="margin">2. Cor. 12 9.</note> 
               <hi>my grace is ſufficient for thee, and my power is made perfect in weaknes.</hi> What he commands as neceſſary to ſalvation, he enables in acceptable meaſure to performe by his gracious aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence.</p>
            <p>I conclude all with that ſaying of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. When he ſaw them diſmaid with the ſight of the <hi>Aegiptian</hi> hoſt, preſſing ſo hard after to deſtroy them;<note n="r" place="margin">Ex. 14 13.14</note> 
               <hi>Feare not</hi> (faith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>ſtand ſtill, and yee ſhall ſee the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Lord.</hi> So ſay I vnto you beloved, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you ſhall ſee the huge hoſt of your rebellious cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, threatning your overthrow and vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; yet deſpaire not of victory: <hi>Feare not, ſtand ſtill, be of good Courage; yee ſhall ſee the great ſalvation of the Lord.</hi> None of them ſo ſtrong; but by reſiſtance, thou ſhalt be enabled to overcome: No duty ſo difficult; but Chriſt ſhall enable thee, in acceptable meaſure, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17320:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
